welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
welcome to another session of the dark
stoa this is an
outdoor session i don't know if you can
hear but we got a bunch of birds
that have joined in this time uh feel
free to message me if that's annoying
and i can find a way to deal with it
um for those of you who are new these
are weekly sessions where we
explore pretty out there
harrowing horrifying essentially
threatening ideas um
and it's through the wisdom of pat ryan
the most dangerous man on the internet
the structure is always the same we have
about a 40 minute lecture where pat
takes us through
first principle reasoning of some out
there
idea with a mic drop moment towards the
end so it's very rewarding that you stay
with the chain of reasoning i want to
encourage everybody to do that
um there's also some secret drinking
games that go on at the same time
and in the part two we get to ask some
questions
so i encourage everybody to even if you
don't follow everything to kind of make
note of things that are unclear
uh especially make note of things that
you want to challenge pat on
and then if you have any interesting
insights then we'll go into a q a round
in part two
last week we talked about alchemy uh
this week actually i'm not sure what
we're on about but this
season is about uh using
principles from the blue church to
dismantle the blue church
if that means anything to you uh and
just a reminder this
uh will be recorded so if you don't want
to show up in the q a period and you
want to ask a question
you can put in the chat and i can ask it
for you and with that
i give you pat ryan
howdy folks welcome back for round four
round four of season two
um this one is going to be about
neuromythologies
um uh neuromyths are
things we tell ourselves when we try to
define the brain
we try to say that oh the brain you've
heard these myths you've heard them they
go like uh
um you use 10 of your brain right that's
a neural myth
that's not actually true you actually
use all your brain um so there's a
collection of these neuro myths that
every civilization
has and it ends up being used to justify
certain actions
and certain moralities and certain
assumptions about the world and society
and
ourselves so it's important when
dismantling a blue church
to attack the neuromythologies that they
utilize as well
so excuse me that's exactly what we'll
be doing tonight
and i'll try to make it worth your time
thanks much and here we go
all right neuromythologies
so this is uh still exploring this meme
we're almost done uh probably one more
of this and
we'll be out of this meme finally um
season one was
talking about the future season two is
talking about now
and in this particular talk we'll be
going over these wonderful concepts
and it's all related to neuromythology
so we gotta start at the beginning with
neuromythology
we're gonna start with egypt so they uh
they practiced mummification as you know
and when they began the mummification
process they would start with pulling
the brain out of the nose
and that would either pull the organ out
or stir it up and then pour it out
whichever
it varied in different regions of egypt
that process is called excelebration
and the reason why they started with the
brain first
um because they didn't understand what
the brain was
and the literal translation of the brain
was skull awful
if you don't know what awful is it's
like it's like the refuse it's like the
garbage meat that you'd buy at a store
or like literal
crap and trash around everywhere it's
literally worthless meat
um so the egyptians thought the brain
was worthless meat
they had no idea they didn't care um
that's the more i think about it i think
that's true of a lot of people
but you know they can be fixed um in
fact there's one case where
they went through a mummy and in the
process of uh of digging out the brain
the tool broke off and it just stayed in
there i don't know i mean they didn't
really care about this stuff at all they
just they didn't they just wanted the
brain out of the head
um and then you know meanwhile they
would preserve other organs like intact
like
really really down in great detail the
kidneys deliver
uh they they dose those in drugs to
really get like embalmed them for as
long as possible but they didn't they
did not want the brain in that skull at
all
so the neuromythology of egypt was the
brain doesn't matter
i guess you gotta start somewhere right
so then we get the grease
where this guy comes along um acmeon
yeah acmeon so so acmeon was known
for dissection of corpses and humans
um and you would threaten people that
chop you up
if you die so he kind of won a lot of
arguments anyway he's the guy who came
along with the idea that the brain was
the seat of human intelligence
he uh poked and prodded around different
uh
war victims for example uh soldiers
coming back from wars or people uh
harmed by soldiers
and noticed that when they had head
damage um they were acting very
differently
their their character had fundamentally
changed their soul was different
and so he was making the correlation
that well maybe this skull awful isn't
what we think it is maybe it's something
specific to intelligence and our very
natures itself
of course it took a lot of head trauma
to make that association
um but humans are slow and i guess we
like ourselves that way
so um he is celebrated in the blue
church
uh because right here in this red box
you'll see
physician basically he said that
physicians should draw conclusions from
empirical observations
instead of divine revelation so this is
more blue church uh
jabbing and seedling the idea that uh
you know we have to
we have to you know science above all
you know and that that's that's blue
church's morality because with science
it can actually
justify their policies and everything
else and
this is this is a hero the blue church
for that
uh then we keep going we get to the
medieval era now aristotle obviously not
medieval era but he was a heavy
influence of the medieval era
his his training and a lot of his
almost everything he wrote was devoured
by most learned
people of that time um so he came up
with the idea of common sense or census
uh
communist uh which is
so he didn't agree that intelligence
came from the brain he thought it came
from the heart
right so he said it was like this heart
thing um and this is where the soul is
and this is where all intelligence comes
from
and the reason of thinking that is
because you can remove a lot of things
from the
from the human body and you don't die
but if you remove the heart you do
you can even remove parts of the brain
and you won't die
so the heart seeing as this like very
fundamental organ they just made the
assumption well that's
that's where the soul is because if i
remove that you're dead it's very easy
logic to come to the conclusion to so
it's not
it's not that his reasoning was faulty
um it's fairly sound really
um although he did say that the brain
was a cooling agent for that soul
which is interesting um he might have
been right
i'll get to that so then galin comes
along
and he says the brain is uh where all
these common senses are actually
co-mingling oh and by the way it's made
entirely of sperm
that i wish i was making that up right
that that was a commonly held opinion
all the way through the middle ages for
multiple cultures like you may have seen
like in china you see like
sometimes you see these cartoons and i
couldn't find it because i couldn't
remember the name of it
i wish i did um but it's usually this
old man
his forehead's like really enlarged and
gorge
and he's like you know he has like a
cane and he's like he's old and he's
always smiling
well the westerners look at that and
think oh what a funny little guy but
everyone in china knows that's a
pervert
his head is full of semen that's what it
means
so he's it's like so this is a this is a
multicultural cot like
commonly held assumption for almost all
of history that the brain was full of
sperm
and to really drive home my point uh
leonardo da vinci would draw anatomy
in which the dick was connected to the
spine because the spine was a tube to
get the sperm out of the brain so it can
shoot out the dick
so this this was really well like
held this whole concept um and i may
have focused on the pp for too long so
let's get back to this part
um so the common senses are co-mingling
in the brain
that was gallon's contribution in
addition to thinking the brain was a
sperm tank
um so so we're we're slowly iterating
here you gotta give these guys credit
um and then descartes comes along and
the car
basically all of us um he comes
along and says
makes a humongous sleep the brain is in
fact not a sperm tank which is very
observant of him thank you
and that the pineal gland is the seat of
the soul
due to its subtle asymmetry now that's
interesting
the idea that most of the brain is
symmetrical
uh is well known and well understood
even by even in pre-modern times
um but the pineal gland is actually a
little bit off it's like a
tiny bit off right so because of that
asymmetry it was actually it's unique in
the brain
and using that reasoning descarte
basically said the pineal grand
pineal gland was the seed of the soul
and of course that that leads to uh
pineal gland
memes meeting with eye of raw memes
because boy they kind of look similar
and then which goes on to mate with
hollywood memes to create illuminati
memes
and all that uh you know it's all fun
and games until you realize
wait a second if you get pineal gland
tumors they actually accelerate puberty
in children
that's uncomfortable so one wonders why
they focus on the pineal gland so much
but anyway um this was considered the
seat of the soul
and held for until i mean they were
doing
penalectomies in the 1920s uh it wasn't
until
they started um trying to figure out
melatonin production
where they would uh take an animal brain
an animal panel gland
blend it down and then you had melatonin
which you could then like they would
inject it into salamander and the
salamander would turn colors
that's how they figured that stuff out
um
but this this is a hell this is still
deeply held by some more wild sex
of of different cults and things as well
so
you know it has a lot of sticky power
that particular neuro myth
um so we get to the modern era now we
can laugh at all that primitive
interpretation of the brain right yeah
we're modern yeah
just kidding we're just as stupid as
they are in fact descartes thought
that the brain was kind of a hydraulic
pump uh freud compared it to a steam
engine
carl uh private thinks it's a
holographic storage device and most
people here think the brain is a
computer
so the i we keep coming up with these
dumb neuro myths they're bad analogies
they don't help
they're feeding bunk science it's all
crap really
and this is by gary marcus who's a
fantastic resource by the way he wrote a
book called
the mind the birth of the mind
i highly recommend it it's a fantastic
book if you're coming from a code or
background like me
um he was able to take some
concepts about information theory and
apply it to the brain without
saying the brain was a computer which
was really masterfully done
it's a fairly old book it's like 1990
something it's a good read i recommend
it
um but he correctly points out that here
here we are doing our best to describe
what is effectively the most complicated
machine we could think of
and say that's just like the brain which
is all throughout history like the most
complicated thing
for its time was a steam engine and the
car's time was a hydraulic pump
and it's stored you know so that's all
we're doing it we're we're just
like thinking the most complicated thing
in engineering is our brain
and we're always wrong about this but
these are neural myths these are things
we tell ourselves about the brain
um and why is this why am i focused on
this weirdness well
because according to this fantastic
study um where they took
educators normal people and people who
were
exposed to actual neuroscience and they
asked them a bunch of neuromythologies
is this true is this not true well 68
of people believed in the
neuromythologies and people who were
actually neuroscience oriented 46
of them believed in the neuromythologies
so it's a really ongoing issue
where we come up with this really bad
analog of the brain and then everybody
uses it
and you can't even question the damn
thing because so many people are
interlocking believing it it's almost
like a holy war to a degree
like there are people running around
thinking the brain is a quantum computer
and if i
call them out on that they'll probably
you know yell at me throw fish at me or
something it's pretty bad
so here's here's an example of these
common neural myths that a lot of people
buy into
left brain versus right brain that's a
very common mythology that people tend
to think like oh
left brain's organized right brain's
artistic and you know they're just
fighting in the middle
no that's not true the brain is way more
complicated than that
uh we only use 10 of our brain that's a
mythology
that this is like oh well you should we
could be using 90
right no you are using 100 of your brain
you just don't have like conscious
control over it and you're lucky
you don't
because if you did have conscious
control over your brain you probably
forget to breathe and fall over
so you don't want to have manual
override on your own nervous system
there's good reason for that
people have learning styles this is one
of those sticky myths don't approach
like
new mothers with this type of
because they buy this stuff and they
will they will yell at you all
day long but there is no such thing as a
learning style
um you learn things unconsciously all
the damn time
like you will we have we have
demonstrably
done this to where people are we can
train someone
on very subtle on very subtle signals to
do something so for example
when i don't like a co-worker um
i'm a very evil person um when i don't
like uh when i don't like a co-worker
i will uh god what what did i do i think
i was like
i would do i would make a noise every
time a certain event happened to the
point that the co-worker started looking
for the noise when
when that event happened but i was just
training his subconscious system
um so people learn even you know
learning isn't this like
i'm going to sit there and hit the
switch and now i'm in learn mode no it
doesn't work that way you you're always
learning
uh brain development ends upon puberty
this is wrong
brain develops it's always going on it's
always going on but this is a common
neural myth
48 of neuroscientists believe this
learning is from new brain cells being
formed
no that's not true
it's it's how they connect it's not it's
not new pathways yes not new brain cells
right
and you were born with a fixed mental
capacity again not true you have to
define what mental capacity is
so these are these are common
mythologies and a lot of people buy this
stuff
and it would be silly in and of itself
because it is
but unfortunately these myths
they become the justification for
policies
like really rushed policies and i'll
give you the most powerful and dangerous
neural myth that we all believe in
in some capacity or another and that's
the neural myth of equality
that is a neuromyth and why is that
under our myth i'll show you
clearly these organs of my body are the
byproduct of intelligence you ignorant
creationists
not the brain brain's magic brain can't
be the product of evolution
because if it is then you're racist
because there's differences in brains
now there's difference in how they
process
oh no now we can't use science for our
precious science
and if we want to use science to protect
our precious science we'll just say
neuroplasticity
they'll say oh my brain will do anything
i'll turn into a bar stool
if i if i just you know change my
plasticity enough
so this is an example of a neuromyth
where the science is pretty strong over
here
but it's intentionally denied over here
and pretty aggressively denied
now admittedly this wasn't done in a
vacuum why this is denied
so we should probably explore how this
got denied so hard
um it's because the neuro myths justify
behavior policies and reactions
so let's start with the wild ass neuro
myth of
the three-fifths compromise that's a
pretty wild neuro myth if you
ask me it's
very dangerous and deadly one too the
idea that black slaves are three-fifths
of a human
obviously not their brain part right
that's the that's the neuro myth
justification
behind slavery and then you have
galton's dream of improving the human
genetic stock
where they want to get rid of the low iq
people and they want to
promote the high iq people again a neuro
myth that is justifying policy
and then a dolphin hortler is running
around he wants to improve the dolphin
genetic stock
again we've we've seen what that how
that turns out that doesn't turn out so
hot
what is his secret plan hmm but you know
these are these are neuro myths the idea
of of the uh the dolphin race having
like a better brain
so you know neuromus they justify really
up policies
so you got to be real careful what
numerous you actually believe in
because that you know on this side is
going to be challenges to this
if the three-fist compromise is
rationality behind slavery then you have
you know
this guy shows up comes up with a couple
of dogs and starts training him to do
complicated actions
i mean if i can train dogs to be
differently obviously we can train
these so-called three-fifths humans you
know so what's the problem here
right
so that's that's a successful challenge
of it right
and then when you're trying to improve
the human genetic stock you just end up
in endless dysgenics
where people are just rebelling against
it
and then jeez now we have to use our
entire civilization to make sure that
that one neuro myth never happens again
so you have to be real careful with what
neuromust you subscribe to because if
you do
if you didn't fall for the trick over
here you'll fall for the reaction
and when white women cry we all know we
gotta we gotta listen
right so we gotta we gotta get our we
gotta get our civilization we're gonna
stop this neuro myth
by using even worse neural myths it's
it's so ass backwards
and then again how does this you know
let's let's keep exploring this
justification why
why we're not allowed to apply evolution
to the brain um
so the observations brains should be uh
treated differently because they're
because they are differently my brain is
not your brain your brain's not my brain
all of our brains are pretty
different that's
that's a no-brainer right so uh
justification
my brains are the best and their brains
are whack that crazy dolphin right
uh and then uh the reaction is all
brains
uh should be all brains are equal and
should be treated the same
that's how you react against the dolphin
so then uh people have dispositions and
preferences that's a fair observation
the dolphin runs comes and says no
there's only the dolphin way and then
the reaction becomes i can train any
human to be anything at any time
then i care about and you know people
care about their tribes a fair
observation
i really care about my tribe at the
expense of someone else's
that's the dolphin that damn dolphins
violent man um and then the reaction is
going to be we should care about peop
all people equally so so what are we
doing we're
we're here we're in the reaction phase
against the neuromyth
we've we've pivoted our entire
civilization to make sure
that this neuromuth isn't allowed to
happen and in the process we've embraced
utter trash neuromyths absolute trash
oh by the way this guy's benefiting from
all of it because he gets cheap labor he
can fire artisanal labor whenever he
wants and everyone's equally worthless
now
so this is this is what happens you this
was a bad neuro myth
we can all mostly agree to that we
that's a kind of
angry dolphin right this is not
a better neuro myth
this is not better just because it's not
this
because it's still resulting in
up things so you got to be careful with
your neural myths
and we are yeah you are here it doesn't
get better from here by the way
sorry
so what is what is this what what what
does the neuro myth manifest
what does it make real what behavior
does it justify
especially in a democratic tradition
where every person is worth the same
vote
no matter what your background is no
matter what your neurology is no matter
what your experiences are you are all
the same vote
and then you mix that up with equality
obsession the neural myth of equality
and then you mix it with psychographic
liberal capitalism and
its clown world clown world all the time
so
obesity is the idea that i'm exactly the
same as someone with
discipline because i'm equal
my neurology is the same that's what
matters right
and then hysteria and guardian heart if
i'm doing bad faith force making
if i'm screaming at you if i'm yelling
at you in a threatening force that is
exactly the same as an intentional stoic
doing sense making
in a world of equality it is exactly the
same
and the reason it's the same is because
of the neuromythology my brain is equal
to your brain
so it doesn't matter what my behavior is
it doesn't matter what i do
because my brain is the same and then
you get
callous altruism and what forest where
equality means
i only need to care about the outliers
and i don't need to care about the
median
and then catharsis denialism and state
and stasis
where it's a never-ending crusade of
redefining the median
you can't get catharsis you can't
actually beat the demons you're
inventing
because if you do then your crusade's
over so we gotta redefine the damn thing
all over the time
so we deny ourselves catharsis so this
is this is the clown world this is what
the neuro myth
has made normalized this is what it made
real and we're all living in this
all the damn time no breaks no exit
no way out and it only gets worse from
here
and this is all because of the neuro
myths we've we've
we've dedicated a warning crusade
against one bad neuro myth
and we are now enabling even worse ones
as a result
so instead of trying to come up with
prescriptions about the brain
and say the brain is this thing and it's
that thing
and trying to champion my personal
neural myth the most i'm gonna
step back and say let's not do that
for the next 10 minutes right let's say
why don't we start looking at not what
the brain
is or what the brain should be or how we
can use
the brain to justify morality how about
we just find the dependencies
of the brain how about we find
the limitations of it because there's a
lot of assumption in a lot of the neural
myths we believe in
that the brain is infinitely plastic it
can do whatever it wants it can
it can be wired here and i i was a chef
yesterday and today i'm a skydiver and
look how plastic my brain is right
um that's that's the mythology we tell
ourselves secretly
and sometimes openly um but let's not do
that let's just find the dependencies
like let's find the structural
limitations of the brain
and figure out from there let's do that
instead so i'll walk you through it
first thing we're going to focus on is
neurons the limitations of neurons
that's a that's a that's a that's a
forbidden phrase in the blue charge
you're not allowed to say for
limitations of neurons because they're
magical and they're always right
um so in this case uh most cells perform
mitosis
but not the neuron neuron does not
perform mitosis
and it has a fully functional nucleus by
the way completely functional
dna is there you know everything's doing
its job just fine
but it doesn't go through mitosis that's
an interesting limitation
and that's indicative of something the
reason we look for the limitations is so
that we understand the structural biases
so that we can understand why the brain
even exists to begin with
because if we're going to put so much
focus on this damn thing and use it to
justify this endless clown world
show that we're in
perhaps it's worth looking into
the cognitive the pressures behind
cognitive evolution
if we're going to endlessly come up with
neural myths you know let's find the
dependencies let's figure out how this
damn thing evolved
and this is a this is a a very good
piece of evidence about how the brain
evolved and why the brain evolved
most more importantly why so this is a
clue
this is a clue and then temperature
most people don't know about brain
temperature they think yeah it's
it's a brain right bro no it is not
you only have one celsius degree
bandwidth to work with
so the brains and the temperature that
it's in and the largest distance between
any part of the brain
if you measure all the temperatures of
all parts of it
between the highest temperature and the
lowest temperature is one
celsius one
that is a remarkably narrow zone
that you have to keep your temperature
in and to keep the brain there
that is a miraculous piece of work in
fact
uh it's uh if you if you get
you know you start bringing your body
temperature up 70 percent of information
that's normally retained is lost
at 35. so if even if you go from
if you start at 36.7 c and you drop
one degree 70 of information is now lost
you're not remembering it just
one degree that's wild right
that is a
crazy crazy narrow fine-tuned result
and then the brain is it's compromise of
two percent of the body mass
takes 25 of your total glucose and 20
oxygen consumption
this is a metabolically demanding organ
with intense heat production
this is generating heat all the time
and even with all of this like firepower
and horsepower
it still has to maintain that tight band
of temperature
and then this one is yeah and different
states of temperature management for
example when you are
deeply anesthetized your temperature
drops your body temperature drops when
you're
an anesthetized the brain temperature
drops i mean um
and when you sleep uh it rises and falls
with sleep as well and arousal as well
so so this is uh this is another clue
why does the brain need this temperature
that's the question you would ask
it's very important to have this it's
doing its best to have it and it's
consuming a tremendous amount of your
biochemistry to make it happen
and yet it's still able to dissipate
heat
like a heat sink like
a finely tuned heat sink
that's really important
and then we look at stimuli a quick
science lesson a photon is a byproduct
of one atom reducing its energetic state
so pew that means for every photon
there's one atom at least
and when we're talking about a light
bulb light bulb at around 100 watts is
generating 300 quintillion photons per
second
so that's uh 300 quintillion atoms
changing their energy state per second
in your eyeball both of your eyes are
only receiving 400 million of that
wait what wait hold on
if you do the math you're only seeing
this much of the light bulb
that's it not just the light bulb
of every single thing you're looking at
you're only seeing that fraction of
reality of me
of your hand put your hand in front of
your face you're only seeing that
percentage of it
where's the other where's all the other
information what the what the where
where did i go turns out your brain
can't handle the truth
because it's too much information
that's a key piece of evidence it's the
stimuli the brain is intentionally
reducing the amount of stimuli that's
available
it's going through a filter process it's
saying it doesn't need everything it
just needs what's important
what's important well we'll get there in
a moment
let's look at the topology of the brain
if you adjust the volume the weight the
size of this brain
that means the neck muscles have to
change the bone structures have to
change
your endocrine system has to change
blood flow changes
it's a it's a structurally expensive
process to fundamentally change your
brain
uh that's why evolution is so damn slow
that's why evolution is so damn slow
it's because of the brain
because in order for the brain to make
any change it has to change the entire
body first
so all of these things have to be
synchronized as they move they have to
move very slowly
because the the dependency chains are
very complicated
and it's three pounds of every reason
you've ever been wrong about anything
ever so you got three pounds
roughly and then the
uh the jerry and the and the sulky they
are not
found in most animals most people think
that the brain
uh that that wrinkling is found in all
animals it's not
it's found in elephants it's found in
humans and is found on like 20 other
species
it doesn't exist for most of the animal
world
and furthermore while this looks random
these little divots in these valleys and
these foldings these foldings
they are consistent between individuals
meaning the foldings in your brain are
very consistent with mine
and this is across races too and genders
so these folds matter it's not just
throwing a bunch of
neuroplastic men it can solve everything
huh no there's
a very specific structure going on here
it's very very specific
so let's look at let's summarize these
dependencies
and so we've analyzed them we've said
okay here are some interesting
limitations about the brain that'll give
us
clues to why the brain even evolved to
begin with
and we're going to start by looking at
where have we seen these problems
elsewhere
so we have footholds to work with as we
explore these these
clues so uh the folding packs more
neurons in the same space that's a
limitation
because your skull is an actual physical
limitation you can't just get more skull
it doesn't work that way
so you gotta pack you gotta really just
stuff that you know it's like stuffing a
shirt in a goddamn like potato chip bag
or something
just you know just crumpling it all in
um where have we seen this activity
before
when it came to miniaturization and
exception driven
chip fabrication you see the same exact
thing you're just packing and packing
reducing and getting it further down
you're stuffing more transistors on the
damn thing you're just just
going balls out as hard as you can using
every hack
and every tiny fractal optimization you
can find
to get more and more on there so there's
a constant pressure
to get neurons as packed as possible
that's a guaranteed given
the neurons that are existing within the
within your body
they are there as a byproduct of your
chemical support your biochemical
support systems what it's actually
maximally capable of given the the
uh the metabolic um
extreme consumption that the brain has
changes in the brain mean changes to the
anatomic and support systems
so like i said i gotta change so many
things if i change one part of my brain
um that's why everything goes so slow
evolution
well we see the exact same problems when
we're engineering for effective escape
velocity
so it's the exact same issue where i
need
fuel to leave the planet but to have
more fuel i need more structure which
means i have more weight which means i
need more fuel to move the more weight
which means i need more structure
because now
now i'm just caught in this loop
of crazy um
and you have to you have to get real
specific about your your mass
your rocket fuel and your velocity
ratios so you can actually achieve
escape velocity it's a very fine-tuned
issue
and the same is true about about
increasing neurological
structures and changes temperatures have
to be within a one celsius zone
that's that's crazy right this is the
same thing we see in finely tuned
sensitive quantum computers
they need to operate at very very
specific temperatures
oh raven here your mic's on um
the uh so this is these are problems
we've seen in other computation devices
and you have to solve for that and we
have massive gamers have
massive heat sinks on their on their
cpus right
neurons can't go through mitosis uh same
thing with
maximum transistor counts you can only
pack so many transistors on to
the uh wafer in fact we get we get to
the point where
we actually can't make transistors any
smaller so you might have noticed that
um cpus have been pegged at three
gigahertz for like the past 20 years
despite all the advances that are going
on breaking that three to four gigahertz
range
well that's because of quantum physics
you actually can't get
less than like six trans like six atoms
for a transistor
because once you go below six atoms and
quantum fluctuations just break the
whole thing apart
so you don't get a reliable band of
electricity going through it
so we found the the most
optimal atomic configuration for the
transistor and now we've pegged our
counts
well the neurons have done the same
thing they cannot go through mitosis
which means
the number of neurons that you have are
optimized it's not like they can go
through mitosis and get
more on demand you you get what you work
with you you get what you have
the brain is not selecting for sensing
atomic reality
remember the photons we can only see so
many of them
it's not seeing atomic reality it's
seeing a holograph
of reality reality is the holograph
right so we see this in compression uh
decompression and psychophysics
algorithms
like the mp3 for example the way the mp3
works why it's so small
typically an mp3 a recorded sound wave
should be like
i don't know 60 to 80 megabytes but an
mp3 gets it down to three
and the way it does it is called
psychophysics so
there's only certain frequencies that we
actually hear with a high level of
clarity and everything
outside of that range is garbage anyway
so we don't need to pack all the
information at the high and the low
frequencies
so you just strip those entirely and
then you just focus on primarily the 2k
to 5k
range of frequency and then you compress
for that
that's a huge part of the mp3 being so
tiny as it is
but it's not the actual song but it
sounds like the actual song it sounds
like the actual recording your brain
doesn't know the difference
so that's that's an example of a
psychophysic algorithm
and it turns out uh for the visual
cortex it's doing the same thing
it's only picking upon reality
that's important that you can care about
and everything else is just garbage that
the brain doesn't care about
and then brains are uh metabolically
greedy and they can imbalance glucose
and oxygen economies uh we've seen this
in
contract enforcement financial
forecasting game theory
you know if you screw my access to
resources i screw your access to
resources type thing
so these are the clues
of the limitations of the brain so we
can actually like
be responsible with our neuro myths
instead of just
being reckless like we have been excuse
me
um and here's some examples of where
we've seen these limitations just to
have an analog to kind of like
get the problem
so we're trying to understand how to
build a responsible neuro myth
so it probably helps to understand what
the brain may be doing
so we're going to start with some some
premises here we're going to say that
inside this bubble this is the permanent
noise factory that is the universe
the universe is just full of information
and matter and matter
and energy and it's all noise it's just
non-stop noise so it shoots out
a photon
from this noise little photon comes out
hits the physical interface of the body
which intercepts the energy and either
moves and either the body moves towards
the energy or away from the energy at
the very minimum
then it goes starts the neural cascade
which then fires roughly at 180 miles
per hour
up your arms or through your nervous
system um and that's converted into
that energy is converted into a neural
equivalent
a neuron equivalent known as stimuli
it's not it's not like the photon is
running through your body it's the
impact of the photon on the nerve
that that's going up your body if it's
if it's heating i should say if it's
heat in particular you'll feel that but
if it's
an optic nerve sorry optics where i'm
you know it's actually hitting the cones
and the rods
it's not the photon literally going in
my brain it's it's the excitation of the
nervous system
but that excitation is a representation
of the photon and that's the important
takeaway there
so then it goes into the brain which i'm
starting to think uh
as in terms of a symbol economy so
i am a collection of atoms
uh and you see my hologram
based on this understanding of energy
exchanges and how the brain is
perceiving reality
and in that hologram it's going into
your eyes
into your brain and you're creating
symbols about me
now why are symbols important symbols
are important because if you had to
constantly update
if you had to constantly see reality at
all times in order to make sense of it
if i just did this
and you didn't have a symbol of me you
had no symbol processing
you would be asking yourself where is
that voice coming from well you already
have a symbol of me in your head
so there you have the representation of
me i don't need to be here at all times
so we're actually we're creating this
like constantly
incorrect and out of date map of reality
in our brains at all times
and it's always it's always out of date
but the brain still works with that
information because it's better than
nothing
even if it's not permanently in sync at
all times that's okay we can we can get
by
we can make it work
and then sorry
then the energy economy those symbols
they require
biochemical consumption of glucose and
oxygen to form
so in your body there is also a
signature being generated for every
symbol you are processing and handling
and dealing with
and that is that is a unique signature
too and if you want to check out um
uh carl fristen that's that's carl
fristan's stuff right there
he's talking all about the free energy
principle and whatnot regarding bayesian
brains
but there is a there is a biochemical
signature of every symbol
in your body every symbol that get gets
made in your mind
and then the thermal economy remember we
have that one band of seed we got to
work with
that's super tight and you got to stick
to that band
so now the biochemical consumption has
to be converted into the thermal
equivalent too
so when you get a symbol in your mind
there's a biochemical consumption and
then there is a thermal consequence
and the and the interaction between
these three things is like a triangle
it's unstable so i should say it's the
most it's the most minimum stability you
need
is a triangle in order for something to
to stay self-regulating
so this is how you are generating the
universe in your brain
roughly and at a mid level not not not a
high level but a mid-level right
so we start with that objective reality
and as we get further and further along
in this process
more and more of objective reality fades
away and as we go more and more on the
process symbolic reality takes over
the hologram the symbolic reality is the
only reality
you've ever had and it's the only
reality
you'll ever have and that's not to say
that we're dumb and we need to fix this
problem
it's the fact that we this isn't even a
problem this is the result
of all of the efficiencies and all of
the equilibrium and all the balance that
our brain has evolved to handle
it doesn't want objective reality that's
going to kill it
it will literally kill the brain trying
to understand objective reality you will
run yourself out of glucose and oxygen
uh pretty quickly if you started seeing
every atom this is bad news
and so from here we get our reality
filter
so the balance between the symbols the
energy and the thermal
creates what it is we're actually
looking for from this permanent noise
maybe we're a bee and we're looking for
flowers maybe we're a crab and we need
uh
we're a hermit crab and we need a shell
maybe we're elephants and it's time to
bang
maybe we want to talk to each other
maybe this wolf is chewing on this lamb
and they're all cute i don't know where
i got that picture but the simple
economies in our head they're
stabilizing
with the energy economics within our
body as well
so the reality you're seeing in
everything you're seeing and everything
you can conceive of
is the signature of economic
efficiencies
that's a wild way that's a hard thing to
grok the idea that reality
looks the way it looks is because that's
the most efficient
balance between energy thermals and
and meat space that's a very very weird
thing to think about
but according to this i might be right
so let's let's let's run with this a
little bit further if we're going to
craft the neuromyth
out of this um the neuron can be seen as
dna bypassing its own structural
limitations
now how can that be we'll take our
we'll take our model we were exploring
look at our our reality filter i'm just
some instead of a you know this whole
thing it's just going to represent it as
this
so here we are my reality filter it's
time for me to interact with reality
i'm going to say ah from this permanent
noise factory i need
i don't know i need a birthday cake okay
so i need a birthday cake whatever i
just need one
so my filter reality i'm going to write
into reality
this very long beautifully exquisitely
manicured
explanation on why i need a birthday
cake right now
very long post but it's cognitively
expensive
to write all this stuff and build it all
up i had to burn a lot of biochem
i had to generate some heat i had to
have that heat piped away
i had to go recalling through my memory
and i had to go through my symbols and
keep my social relations on track
this is a cognitively expensive
operation
and when i throw it into this void
nothing comes out
not a damn thing comes out so i spent
all those resources
and i got nothing and i still need a
birthday cake
okay let's change my messaging
this is cognitively cheap oh look
six brains popped out the void well holy
there is a economic game going on
in our communication that is driven
entirely by this
and this this is cognitively cheap
i just said one word and now i got six
brains i had the attention of six brains
i got you i got you all and it wasn't
expensive for me
now somebody get me this cake
that was it so now i've been able to
command from the void
the thing that i needed so evolution
cannot optimize neurons any further
due to these economic limitations
instead
it is selected for neurons to summon
each other
so so the idea of making a cyber brain
is a joke it's pointless the idea that
we can just change evolution and we get
a better brain that's that's a joke too
because we see the economic costs
associated with all that all the complex
bean counting and balancing that's
associated with it you can't do it
anymore
so the neuron has bypassed dna dna goes
through the evolutionary process in a
random haphazard manner
the neuron says nah no no no screw that
we got our own way thanks and what we're
going to do is we're going to summon
other neurons for our moment for
hey come here do this thing okay great
so we're actually optimizing for
communication and socialization and
getting to know one another
so with that said we can now make a shot
at a neural myth proposal
i'm going to call it cognitive
thermodynamics so here's how it works
you have input it's energy mass that's
the input
and they have the output which is
emotional behavior
as neural summoning as neuron summoning
so it's i'm not
if i'm if i'm yelling at someone it's
not because i'm emotional as if i'm
if i'm happy and i'm laughing it's not
not because i'm emotional
my emotions are serving a purpose
they're serving a function
they actually do something and what they
do
is that is the shortcut the brain has
figured out
to summon more neurons so hey i have
this emotion you see the emotion
you're either attracted or you're
repulsed by it if you're attracted great
now we can share neurons
now we can actually share cognitive
space we can tell stories we can do all
these things and we can work together i
can offload my cognitive demand onto you
and now we're working in parallel that
is a very much
easier solution than trying to grow my
brain bigger
and it's a lot less dangerous too unless
i'm an asshole and then you punch me and
then maybe the neuron summoning needs to
take a chill for a bit
but what about all the stuff that input
so this this implies an input and an
output
what about all the stuff i'm taking in
that doesn't become behavior
where does that go well that's heat
it's ideas thoughts symbols
so all of our ideas are heat
the brain evolved like a heatsink
that's the parallel so why this neuro
myth is useful
is because it actually destroys all the
bad
neural myths it completely eliminates
them
now how can it do that well for starters
uh the behaviors trash can go kick rocks
uh they're running around saying inputs
everything and i if i control the
environment i control the brain
and they have some pretty compelling
science behind that yes it's true
um but i don't like you as a human so
off
and then we have uh then you have the
incomplete moral doctrines determining
what your behavior should be you know
your behavior should be this and you
should do that you should this
well they can go kick rocks too because
now my emotional behavior has a purpose
there's a reason behind it and so if i
start looking at my neural myth like
this
instead of saying i have to subscribe to
or defeat some moral doctrine
no i know what emotions are doing now i
know what their function is i know what
it's supposed to be
okay it's just neuron summoning simple
and then bye bye hyper individualism so
instead of your ideas and your thoughts
being a representation of you as a
person and your personality being so
bound up and the holographs you're
consuming get the out of here it's
just heat
so what we've done is we've eliminated
all the neural myths
by embracing this one so your brain is
no longer your identity
you're not in descartes prison any
longer you are free
and it was a cooling agent after all he
was right
that's it thanks folks
well thanks again pat for another
the brain bending session um
i think like a background message and
what you're saying
that i want to clarify is that all
are you suggesting that all explanations
because they're fundamentally like in
that symbolic realm not objective realm
are
destined to be normates like we'll never
actually touch what's going on
you're on you thanks the neuro myth is
exclusively
the series of collections we try to
attach
to the brain in the hopes to understand
it um
regarding the simulation uh that we have
the holograms and the symbols
of the of reality i mean i ran through
the numbers and you're not seeing the
whole light bulb right so what are you
seeing
um well what you're seeing for is you're
what you're extracting from reality are
things that comport
to your neural summoning strategies
so it could be mating it could be
finding friends it could be working
with people whatever so your your neuron
summoning strategies because the neuron
has hijacked
dna at this point it says no we're gonna
we're gonna change this up
um it hijacked it in the sense that um
it
started driving the show a little bit in
terms of
economic equilibrium internally all the
biochemistry so
um in the process of doing so the neural
summoning behavior you're engaging in
that we've been all engaging in for at
least the last million years
has been very much towards tribal
attitudes uh you know
dumbar number tribes and stuff like that
so
um in terms of
that being a hologram yeah it's a
hologram but it's also the only damn
thing you'll ever know
and that's okay i mean not out here
trying to
rationalize camus or come up with stuff
like that but
um but ultimately the the general
conclusion
is that yes it's a hologram yes it's all
you're going to know it's okay that it's
all you're going to know
and trying to think that you can find
more you might you can you know there
are techniques we have to explore that
objective space to see what's repeatable
according to scientific method and then
we have alchemy which you can use to
figure out the black boxes
we have a whole ecosystem of tools that
are now at our disposal to use and we
should be using all of them
so we shouldn't be relying on these eco
these um these neural myths
to uh to do the driving for us anymore
there's there's almost no point
i i guess that's what i'm saying um just
a reminder to everyone in the room
um just if you have any questions drop
them in the chat and
call on you to ask them i'm gonna keep
going with some of my own
in the meantime um
i guess uh one of the things i'm curious
about is
if you have a definition of fitness here
i know you didn't really use that word
but that
was what i was thinking about um like is
it darwinian fitness is a
fitness of you know ideas that are able
to replicate
uh because of the wide diversity of
neurology that exists on this planet and
you
i'm almost i almost said the n-word with
neanderthal but i didn't so you don't
drink
given the wide variety of you got to
take a half sip i didn't finish that
sentence
um uh the uh the wide variety of
of neurology that exists what that's
indicative of
is it's showing all kinds of
thermal survival strategies it's all
kinds of different heat sinks doing
what it is that they're that their
behavior and their
bio organic um i'm sorry their
biochemical
consumption is com is is making possible
so it's not that fitness fitness might
not have ever
been a thing um it's just the if you
look at the entire species performing an
activity
instead of just inter interpersonal um
uh interaction between competition
either for mating or for food or for
territory
even that um is part of the thermal
equilibrium that the brain is trying to
do remember
all the simple processing is cognitively
expensive it's it's energetically
expensive
so i need to do neuron summoning to
maximize my input so i can keep my brain
running
so the brain is like this it's like this
bicycle it has to keep moving
and if you stop pedaling it all slows
down falls over i need those resources
to keep my brain going and i need to go
out there and cooperate and hunt
and compete and all those types of
things so fitness
fitness might be too too granular
i'm talking there's something even above
that and that's and that's this this
thermal pressure
this uh this energy thermal pressure
come not competition but this
this balancing between symbols and
thermal and energy consumption
that's what's driving the whole show so
with that i know that
you know the the grand devil entropy is
somewhere around the corner here
right all that out for us yeah so um
entropy here
is like uh i mean this is
this is all you know the whole thing is
driven by entropy to a degree
um but this is kind of a way to where
um how can i put this it's not that a
fitness is happening it's not that it's
a
glorious fight against entropy think of
it more like
if entropy is always there reducing
everything down
to the minimum that's all it's not it's
not increasing disorder
it's constantly reducing down to the
indivisibles is trying to take any
complicated system and say
shake you down what's left you know
what's left okay just these atoms that's
what's left okay let's rebuild from
there right
so if you go through that process with
that entropic driver
and so much energy and so much matter
going on in the universe
what you end up with is infinite
possible combinations of what can
endure infinite possible combinations of
what is able to resist against this
entropic shaking down to irreducibles
and so the neuron appears to be one of
the better strategies
in terms of achieving that so it's it's
it is absolutely a child of entropy for
sure
just like dna is all right we got a few
questions coming in
in the chat uh last one for me is
related to
ai and i think you kind of made a
comment about this about how
creating like cyber brains is a waste of
time i don't know if that's has anything
to do with ai
um but i would what i got from that
and correct me if i'm wrong are you
suggesting that there is
nothing more efficient than
what evolution has produced and i guess
my
like follow-up to that is what if what
if evolution just
reached some sort of local maximum and
there's actually a global maximum
somewhere else that we could potentially
reach
the key here is to make sure you're
defining your your
parameters for optimization and
efficiency here
so can we get better efficiency
um in the brain by changing its
configuration
structure no and i'm gonna that's a
shocking answer to most people i know
and the reason i'm saying no
is because any attempt to improve
efficiency of the brain is not actually
improving the efficiency of the brain
what you're doing is you're selecting
for certain combinations of the brain
that are more beneficial than other ones
so you're not actually improving
efficiency here
if i decide to say well let's remove
this part of the brain that controls
i don't know belief in god for example
there's a whole army of people who would
say
yeah that's pretty efficient in fact
there's 68
i actually know the number 68 percent of
people would say that's efficient
because it's a neuro myth right
so um the
removing that who does it create
efficiency for is it creating efficiency
for the person
well that person doesn't have a belief
system anymore so
what's the penalty what's the what's the
thermal penalty what's the energy
penalty
how is that person engaging in neuron
summoning what what types of
we aren't talking efficiency anymore
what we're talking about is
is a circular uh zero-sum game really
where you have i eliminate that part of
the brain now i fit better
in this system i mean we've seen this
all the time with the
pharmaceutical psychopharmaceuticals i
mean that's technically doing what
you're asking where it's shutting down
parts of the brain or enhancing it or
making certain emotions not appear
is that efficiency that doesn't strike
me as efficiency
so you know we've seen what what neuro
tinkering does uh getting finer control
over it and not having to bombard the
brain with like a pack of
i don't know i don't know what all the
kids are doing these days heroin you
know just like
dousing the brain and these type of
drugs um
sure that might be a bit carpet bombing
solution
um but i don't think snipers are gonna
get you any better because you're just
shutting down parts of the brain
that evolve for a very specific reason
so if you're talking efficiency you
first have to define your economic order
that you're selecting
for really well clearly
you haven't tried modafinil pad i have
not
all right um i'm going to hand the next
question over to hannah
and she has a question about the
collective consciousness hannah do you
want to meet yourself
yeah uh and i can try to give a
definition of that if needed
but i'm kind of wondering where it fits
in terms of like
is it more on the neuro mythology side
or is it more on the neuron summoning
like is it a methodology of doing that
so
the concept of collective intelligence
yeah
that's a very good point it could be a
little bit of both as well there there's
definitely
plenty of neuromythology around coming
together in collective intelligence in
the internet and this type of stuff
there's almost endless amounts of
neuromythology around that concept
is there truth to it yes there is truth
to it the idea of when you
when you do the neuron summoning you get
the brains together and the brains do
the thing
that's real that's what we've selected
for um
so yeah we do have a collective uh
intelligence making sense making process
it's very tribal it's very early and we
use it all the time
uh we actually our entire concept of
aesthetics and beauty actually comes
from that as well
so the uh uh that does absolutely exist
can
it go beyond dunbar's number well yeah
it can if you
reduce the amount of information that
you need to track about a person
so for example if i'm if i'm looking at
uh
i can know 300 people in dunbar's number
but i only but i can know like 20
000 unique words for example um that's
quite the mismatch right that's a huge
mismatch that's because words are
neurologically cheap and faces are
neurologically expensive
dunbar's number isn't just like a
constant in a script where you say 300
and that's it
that that number is a peak
is a is an emergent peak in this
equilibrium system between symbols
energy consumption
and thermals so that number is that way
because of how you process symbols
and that's another one of those clues
about how the brain is working and why
it evolved as well
so if i'm tracking 300 faces
and i know them all in detail and i know
the personalities and i know their
relationships that that is the
collective intelligence sense making
you're talking about
if i reduce the amount of information
about a person
if i say well that's bob and that's joe
and that's
sally and say okay i got those people
but if i wanted to reduce their
information i would say oh
they're all democrats so what you're
doing is you're creating a symbol for
all three of those people but the
problem of making simplified symbols is
that that falls prey to the tribalism
as well you say oh this symbol's bad and
everybody associated with that symbol is
bad
and so this is this is what constantly
breaks
the collective intelligence sense making
process uh because we use symbols to
shortcut this whole thing
to keep track of it all but they also
fall prey to tribal
um tribal behavior as well so um
people try they i mean we're always
trying our best
to maximize uh neural summoning that's
what empire is that's what
civilizations are their attempts at
maximizing
um neural summoning basically but uh
if you mismanage it and it gets really
easy to mismanage well
your ability to summon neurons go
bye-bye with it so
empires rise empires fall as they say
if i may i want to have a follow-up to
hannah's question so the way i
understood
collective consciousness was more so
the subjective experience that people
sometimes report of
on psychedelics or after meditation of
being all
one being and realizing that
consciousness is some sort of
distributed thing that expands beyond
our
selfhood and i'm wondering if you have
any thoughts on that
there there is some pretty strong um
there's some very strong evidence in the
fmri space that shows when one is
intentional about their thoughts
you are focusing on different domains of
data and you're focusing on different
domains of stimuli
so for example if i wanted to if you
like if you if everyone sat here for a
second just like
breathed and then just said i'm now
going to focus on my heartbeat
you can actually slow down your own
heartbeat for example right now you're
not you're not doing this consciously
it's not like you're pitting us it's not
like
i grab heart and you know i'm actually
controlling a very
complicated biomechanical orchestration
in my own body and i couldn't tell you
how the i'm doing it
i couldn't tell you like this is the
machine i press and i use these fingers
and i didn't i couldn't even tell you
how i do it but i can do it
so when you're wherever your focus is
and your attention
is you're going to extract all the
information from it as if it was a human
face
so here's what i mean by that the human
face has a pile of information
associated with it
which means that's what we're used to
consuming so if i put my attention
anywhere
else all the information i'm getting
from that focus
is equivalent to the information i would
get from a human face
so if i'm focusing on my heart i'm
focusing on all the complicated
around it too
i'm watching for all the like the tiny
little did the smile
turn a certain way is his head turned a
certain way all that subtle nuance we're
constantly processing
well now i've steered it into my heart
i've steered it into my programming i've
steered it into my work
or i've steered it onto this this mental
experience that i'm having
so yes we we have a huge capacity to
just drink
data from whatever it is we're focusing
on because of the human face thing
the the neural summoning that we're
always uh checking for uh so as a result
you're
if you take that focus and you put it
somewhere else you're going to see
and feel and do you can't
explain
quips would you like to ask your
question on overclocking
um sure um what was it
i think me and anjan had similar
questions so i might read out both of
ours if that's okay
sorry just your avatar is killing me my
bad
um uh i think yeah i said uh can we
overclock the brain by using future tech
to manage and mitigate these limitations
uh overclocking uh yeah overclocking
basically means consuming more
biochemistry
um so as long as you have this like tube
of glucose that's just dumped right
directly into your neck when you
overclock it then maybe
i was about to say because someone said
just strap heat six to your head quickly
but um i i imagine it would be more
complex than that you would have yeah
biology uh heat thermodynamic
many different factors to to actually
manage and mitigate
yeah that's a lot if you don't mind
daniel i was just about to type in a
second question may i ask you
go for it um my second question is it
seems like
the limitation hacks that you've been
mentioning on how the brain
has gotten or gotten away with observing
so much with so little data
um lean it leans heavily on
multiple brains interacting you said
mentioned like these emotional outbursts
and stuff like that
affecting wants and needs and desires
upon other
you know interactive brains does do
these hacks
fall apart in a hypothetical situation
where there is exactly one brain in
existence
uh the thing about uh i mean that's a
that's a hypothetical
fun thought experiment that you can
control and i've seen some of the more
barbaric attempts at trying to recreate
that experiment
um if you put someone in solitary
confinement for example
or someone is born without the ability
to engage
in um seeing or hearing or their sensory
information is gone so that's that's a
close proximity
to that scenario where a person is born
completely sense
sense dead uh yet they're alive
so in those cases because the brain
the brain did not evolve on its own
in isolation in a vacuum it is carrying
the perceptions the instructions and all
of the equilibriums
um that that shaped it it's carrying it
with it
so it's still going to operate in a
human sense looking for those human
things engaging in the human ways
um because the brain really does have
its own opinion on how things should be
perceived
memetic caper would you like to ask your
question
yeah um so if our brain's output
is merely tactics for summoning more
neurons
might such tactics take on a life of
their own
are symbols merely a byproduct or might
they be the instantiation
of neural summoning tactics abstracted
from individual brains
right so the thing about um and that
that goes into some of my earlier
theories regarding
the formation of morality um and why
that
thing kind of keeps happening to us and
why we even do normal myths at all
we know that neuromyths the collection
of symbols that do make up neuromyths
do lead to pretty wild-ass behavior
so yes what happens is when we make
these symbols
in our mind and then we have our
behavior coming out and it's attracting
more neurons because that's what we're
ultimately selecting for
that's going to create more symbols that
we have to manage and if that symbol
just happens to
lead or represent or make a bunch of
people act a certain way repeatedly
we're going to rely on that symbol
this is this is why you see religions
use religious symbology all the damn
time it's a it's a very quick it's a
very quick way to pass
that neuron summoning lesson
without having to reteach it over and
over and over again per generation you
just simply pass the symbol down to the
next generation and poof
everything is already encoded ready to
go locked in
programmed in ready to rock um so even
that is an efficiency so
these symbols do take lives of their own
yes that's true
um andrew you had a question earlier i'm
just going to paste it again
in the chat would you like to ask it
about drugs and or meditation oh yeah
uh because you're talking about uh
objective
reality like the brain can't uh
uh doesn't have objective reality or i
was wondering if drug if you think
that drugs and or like meditation is
like an attempt
to have objective reality and is that
youthful
it kind so i think uh think of it like
this um this camera that's looking at me
right now you see
a square right so everything in this
square is
kind of me except this stuff this is not
me um and then everything outside of
that square is
who knows what it is it could be
anything all i have to do is move my
camera and you see it but you don't know
so there's a there's a limitation to the
information you can take in from this
square
if i modify the electronics on that
thing
i might get a different interpretation i
could get a different filter a color a
different hue
maybe i can put an ar thing on top of it
maybe i can modify the image somehow if
i start tinkering with the internal
electronics but there's no tinkering
that's actually going to expand this box
you have to physically change the
hardware of that camera in order to
expand the box
so if if the drugs aren't changing the
hardware or at least
if they are changing the hardware if
they're not changing them in a
meaningful way that allows you to take
in
more neurons and thus expand this box
um then you're not going to get
objective reality because because
because even before the information hits
your brain your senses are already doing
hard filters on the amount of
information you can get
um and so as a result you're you're kind
of
you're kind of at the whim of that oh
uh so like this kind of
uh uh kind of just for me to grasp this
is it like
that drugs are just kind of changing the
perception but not
the objectible reality yes that's
correct yes
so the drugs are changing
they are physically changing the brain
too lsd is notorious for that
um and there has been endless amounts of
studying into lsd to try to do exactly
what you're talking about
uh between the germans and the cia they
were dumping lsd on every goddamn living
thing on this planet
in the hopes to create a super brain
that could see objective reality every
single one of those experiments failed
by the way
um they did not work at all and they got
into more disastrous
and insane and insidious types of
trialing in order to try and somehow
keep that hope alive
but they're unlimited money
unaccountable assholes
they're getting to the point where
they're dumping lsd and kids for god's
sakes
so it was it was a disaster and
they never achieved that dream they
never got it
so um we could argue that perhaps their
techniques were wrong which
they were we could make the assumption
that perhaps a better chemical needs to
be
evolved and that will magically change
the brain maybe crispr will do it maybe
this will do it
yeah that'll do it um for sure i mean
i know the neanderthal brain process
drink a drink um
we we use crispr for that and it does
physically change the brain the neurons
themselves look like popcorn
like they don't look that's not an axon
it's not a dendrite
it's popcorn nobody expected that um
so yeah you can crisper and change stuff
but that's not the point here the point
is you still have to account
for the for the energy consumption and
the thermal management as well
just you know changing the brain itself
isn't enough you have to you have to get
the equilibrium of everything that makes
the brain possible also right at the
same time
next week can we do the dark stella on
acid
i can do this the whole study on it yeah
i think it might be
the timing might be good everyone else
on acid oh i don't know
okay uh second last question
um angen you had a question about
planning our lives in light of
some of the things that pat says can you
ask that question
hey thanks pat that was an incredible
lecture um
i'll just read my question um you've
mentioned that the coming century
is a century of psychology and
neuroscience that it's hidden inflection
point
why what's the inflection point and what
are the implications for that
in planning our own lives yeah um
the inflection point is that we have
done the maximum amount of neuron
summoning we can do
in our empire building games and with
the advent of the nuclear weapon
our ability to explore more neuron
summoning has completely evaporated
meaning we cannot use geopolitics to
solve our neuron shortage problems
anymore
and when we do play geopolitics to solve
our neuron shortage problem
uh what ultimately ends up happening is
um
it results in dunbar number violations
and cultural conflict and unstable stuff
there i mean i can point to any number
of genocides in any
number of places i'll throw a dart
somewhere in a genocide happen because
of
of cultural conflict um so we've uh
we've hit our hard limits here and so
we've double
tripled quadruple down on trying to
create good enough
neurons with silicon and that's been
going okay
that's been doing some stuff but the
real win here for silicon
is the fact that a.i came or neural
networks came on board
i mean send the name neural network the
bastard child of the neuron
um so what this is allowing us to do is
it's allowing us to overcome certain
parts
of our neuron shortage not all of them
um but
just certain parts of it and the parts
that it allows us to cover
right now is the genomic space because
there's so much data associated with uh
dna research and so much about genomics
um
the art of the the artificial neurons uh
are
assisting us into going into that space
and once we start connecting genomics to
connectomics
and we can start making predictions on
that we're at the inflection point it's
it's over
right so um what does this mean for our
daily lives
uh i mean if you're really close
to the stuff that i'm talking about um
it wouldn't hurt to listen to some of
these lectures first
uh before you start playing crisper
brain games uh
i've been there i can tell you how it
goes um but the uh
for the average person who's looking at
this stuff um
there's a reason i'm promoting alchemy
it's the safest thing you can embrace
it's the safest neuro myth you can
embrace
uh because you're going to see chimeric
cognition you're going to see
bots running around that look and act
just like humans
um you're going to see humans going
psychotic
in this place at the same time uh so the
alchemical neuro myth is actually a
useful way to navigate this upcoming
insanity when we start dealing with
different when we lose our we're going
to lose our monopoly on sentience
um and when we lose that monopoly um we
don't know what that looks like
we don't know how to act about that i'm
i'm not i don't think we're gonna act
very kindly about that
uh and so these chimeric brains and
these
ai brains are going to be running around
making interpretations of law and
morality and they're going to influence
us and we're going to be like where's
the democratic process
giraffe slug raven brain um and it's
going to be like well what
i have no idea and well who do you even
petition in such a situation
uh so so the the alchemical neuro myth
is a good start
to um start looking into in order to
keep your sanity in this in this
mess that's coming up
all right uh key bring us home with the
last question
hi thank you
for the presentation as always um
okay you keep saying bring us home
i don't need to be the last question i
really do not i'm gonna say that out
loud right now
like i understand this tradition
peter referred to it as a ritual i'm
just putting it out there in the
recording
i don't need to be the last question
thanks guys
like you can ignore my question if you
want it's okay um yep
and then there was something about
straightening the picture that'd be
great you know it's okay
you know behind you yeah though that
came up a couple of times i'm sorry it's
it comes into my brain um while i'm
reading and then there was also a
question by todd
about temperature differentials and i'd
like to say that i value air
conditioning a lot now and my friend has
said the same
so thank you for that um i will read
todd's question because i appreciated it
a lot which was
um are there any psychological states
that improve our temperature
differentials i'd assume anxiety
depression and other
mental states disabled capacity i really
like that question i just want to keep
it
there while coming to the question that
i asked which was
oh i wanted to thank you for speaking of
being
intentional about our thoughts that's
been really important to me um
recently in the past and continuing
onwards the question is
you mentioned are we optimizing for
communication
and getting to know one another um
or for birthday cake or
or um the attempt okay so
the attempt to see objective reality um
that's
much appreciated knowing that we only
see 0.000 however many zeros six percent
of photons
um and wanting to understand reality
more great
um do we do that via neuronsemine which
you've already said
a lot about which i'm still processing
to be honest or do we do that through
meditation
and that's great because andrew brought
that up but is it a worthwhile goal even
to be able
to see objective reality
right so um first uh the first part
about modifying brain temperature
uh yeah we actually do that all the time
whenever we go to sleep you go to sleep
and your brain temperature goes big
it goes down um and then when you're on
um
anesthetics when they knock you out your
brain temperature goes down um so there
i'm
i'm sure with those two things there are
drugs that can emulate
that maybe even being drunk brings your
brain temperature down um
but also you know it's it it doesn't
just target the brain temperature
the reason the temperature is going down
is because the the bio
the biochemical fuel is burning less um
so as a result temperature goes down
so you're not engaging in symbol
management any longer
or at least another part of your brain
is going into single symbol management
mode while the other parts don't
so there's there is definitely
reproducible um
biochemical evidence of of modifying
brain temperature
i don't know if it's as simple as
willpower i suspect there may
be some willpower trip tips that you can
do
that can either reduce or bring it up um
when you're in a state of anxiety
for sure because your brain temperature
is going up because your endocrine
system is on fire your adrenaline's
going on
so you're you're getting more details
about reality so that in turn is
burning more glucose and oxygen um so
yes that will increase the temperature
of the brain but but your fluctuation is
going to be
uh within that one c band for the most
part for the most part
um uh if it goes beyond that then you
lose 70 of all information that's going
on anyway
so it's uh it's yes there are there are
ramifications about brain temperature
and depression for sure
then the second about optimizing it
trying to see reality are we
are we optimizing for each other are we
optimizing for birthday gig
i would say why not both but i think
it's we are optimizing for each other to
get the birthday
cake um because to get a birthday cake
is a lot of
it's a lot of work you gotta gotta farm
the grain you gotta beat down the grain
you gotta cook the damn thing but you
gotta get the logs to cook it then you
gotta start the fire but then you need
the metal to start to fire okay well now
i'm cooking it but then i need a
the place that can actually do the
cooking and and now i need uh
i need a cow so i can get some milk to
get some butter in that thing too and i
got to go find a cow and
you know you know convince it to give me
milk
and then i gotta let it age and process
it there's a lot of
complicated economic factors that make
that birthday kick
and so in order to get that birthday
cake we had to select for ourselves
because we need this economy to work in
order to make the birthday cake
so by selecting for ourselves that's how
we got it um so not actually
if you're optimizing for the birthday
cake think of it like this right the
more complicated like
i say that entropy is the process of
reducing down to irreducibles if this is
your base state this is like
atoms right there's a small tribe like
the further we get from the base state
the more unstable things become
before entropy comes by and just grinds
us back down
so the birthday cake is like like here
right you need to have a functioning
civilization to make a birthday cake
that's that's quite the dependency um
but to get that functioning civilization
you you need people selecting for
each other and so the the last part of
that question is this even worthwhile is
is the civilization that generates
birthday cakes worthwhile
i don't think so but that's just me um i
i think civilization can do some other
interesting things that we've forgotten
how to do
uh maybe it'd be nice to take a break
from the birthday cake every so often
um but that's a matter of personal taste
so
you know you can dismiss that i think
it's i think it's probably up to each
individual to figure out what it is they
want from the civilization because it's
the only game in town
so you better you know make peace with
it somehow
all right awesome answer thank you so
much for going into details
yep thanks kee for your
final question and thanks pat again for
another wonderful session
thanks everybody for partaking i'm just
going to hand it over to peter
who's actually right next to me
somewhere
to plug some events and then we'll close
it up
cool thank you daniel thank you
uh pat um so i'll just plug one uh
tomorrow we have vince horn from uh
the famous podcast buddhist geeks it's
coming at 3 pm eastern time to do
a session on social meditation i'll just
read a
part of the copy meditation is bringing
attention to experience and training and
meditation is training and attention
by this definition neither isolation nor
silence is required
we can train together and that is good
because together is what we were born
for
so if that uh appeals to you you can
rsvp on the website bestowa.ca
cool and on that note let's call it
thanks again for another wonderful
session of the dark store see you all
next week
see you around thanks pat
my pleasure